<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Lectio 58, de Trinitate</title>
        <author xml:id="PP">Petrus Plaoul</author>
        <editor xml:id="JW">Jeffrey C. Witt</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.0.0-dev">
          <title>Lectio 58, de Trinitate</title>
          <date when="2014-07-31">July 31, 2024</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>SCTA</authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike  4.0  International  (CC  BY-NC-SA  4.0)</ref></p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="R" n="reims">Reims</witness>
          <witness xml:id="V" n="vat">Vatican</witness>
          <witness xml:id="S" n="sorb">Sorbonne</witness>
          <witness xml:id="SV" n="svict">St. Victor</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-critical-1.0.0" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/1.0.0/src/out/critical.rng"/>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0 guidelines for a critical edition.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2024-07-31" status="draft" n="0.0.0">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>  
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="lectio58">
        <head xml:id="l58-Hldtldt">Lectio 58, de Trinitate</head>
        <div xml:id="l58-Dd1e109">
          <head xml:id="l58-Hqcsspp">How the plurality of persons stands with the simplicity of the divine essence</head>
          <p xml:id="l58-aqtrah">
            The article which is treated, namely, 
            the article of the most sacred and blessed Trinity
            is the principal and fundamental article of the christian religion. 
            
            For though the ancient philosophers and some sects are in agreement with some articles, 
            nevertheless they disagree with respect to this article.
            
            It is the principal article because from this article 
            other articles draw their origin, 
            such as the article of the incarnation and many others, 
            and from this article the sacraments draw their efficacy and their merit, 
            therefore regarding this article there should be a special focus.
            
            And in this matter the entire difficulty resolves to one point, 
            namely, how can the plurality of persons stand with the simplicity of the divine 
            essence. 
            
            And all doctors treating this matter are particularly focused on this question.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="l58-ebccpt">
            And briefly regarding this matter
            <ref xml:id="l58-Rd1e121">
                <name>Bothius</name>,
                who wrote a book 
                <title>on the Trinity</title> 
                through the entire effort in book 2
              </ref>
             does not intend to do anything other than 
             show the simplicity of the divine essence 
             and consequently the simplicity of the persons of the trinity.
          </p> 
          <p xml:id="l58-eaisig">
            And 
            
              <ref xml:id="l58-Rd1e136">
                <name>Augustine</name>
                in his book <title>on the Trinity</title></ref>
             
            recites three causes of erring about the article of the Trinity.
            
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="l58-Qd1e139">
                The first cause is because 
                we attribute to God 
                that which we experience in bodily creatures.
              </quote>
            </cit>
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="l58-Qd1e147">
                The second cause is because 
                we attribute to God 
                that which we experience in spiritual creatures.
              </quote>
            </cit>
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="l58-Qd1e153">
                The third cause is because 
                some people presumptuously 
                attribute to God something which belongs to no other things 
                for example that he could generate himself
              </quote>
            </cit>.
          </p> 
          <p xml:id="l58-qaddes">
            With respect to the first two modes
            the cause of erring is removed through 
            <cit>
              <ref xml:id="l58-Rxxzz1">
                the two first principles posited in the preceding lectures
              </ref>
            </cit>.
            
            Whence because God is immeasurable and infinite, 
            therefore there are properties and conditions 
            which are suitable to him that are not from creatures.
            
            Whence
            <cit>
              <ref xml:id="l58-Rd1e152">
                <name>Aristotle</name>
                in book I of the 
                <title>Physics</title>
              </ref>
            </cit> 
            arguing against the opinion of <name xml:id="l58-Nd1e170">Anaxagoras</name>,
            who posited and infinity of principles, 
            says that the infinite qua infinite is unknown. 
            
            And from this fact it is held that the properties of the divine essence,
            insofar as this essence is infinite, 
            are unknown.
            
            And this is true with respect to intellectual creatures 
            because our eye or our intellect 
            is being oriented toward the greatest secret of nature, 
            namely to God, just as the eye of an owl is oriented toward the light of the sun.
            
            With respect to the third cause of erring
            one is persuaded by the philosopher, himself having been sufficiently elevated, <!-- transl review needed here -->
            that in the matter of the Trinity 
            one should speak without any presumption, 
            but instead with every humility, 
            as <name>Augustine</name> says.
            
            For if there were some effective cause 
            and finite producible effects were precisely known from it, 
            nevertheless it should not be denied by a philosopher that <!-- transl review needed -->
            <c>a</c> and <c>b</c> and <c>c</c> would be able to produce effects.  
            
            And therefore a philosopher would at least be reduced to this 
            that he would not have to deny that the divine essence is in three supposites 
            and that the divine essence is the subsistence of three supposites , 
            and that the article is not evidently impossible. 
            
            And it is necessary to establish and make plausible and article of this type 
            and briefly the simplicity of the divine essence should most especially be insisted upon.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="l58-Dd1e203">
          <head xml:id="l58-Htdrdra">tria de ratione aeternitatis</head>
          <p xml:id="l58-cemdst">
            Therefore, 
            while continuing the matter about divine duration,
            and I add something here about the divine ability to be in place,
            there are three things that should be known about 
            the nature of divine eternity and duration.
          </p>
          <!-- this list of three follows ripa very closely: 
            see https://books.google.com/books?id=RaoAAAAAMAAJ&pg=PA691 
            see distincdtion 9.
            -->
          <p xml:id="l58-peqane">
            The first is that eternity does not the measure of something with potentiality. 
            This is to say that it does not measure something that is able to not be.
            Rather it is a measure of that which is actually, necessarily, existing.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="l58-sdrish">
            The second thing regarding the nature of eternity is that it is a universal measure. 
            This means that it measures how it is intrinsically or is able to be, 
            and whatever is able to be in it intrinsically, 
            and how a thing would be able to be disposed intrinsically.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="l58-tdrnpa">
            <!-- ripa vat ms, folio 148v for parallel -->
            The third thing regarding the nature of eternity is that 
            in the genus of measures it is first effectively, productively, 
            and absolutely first before any other measure.
            Therefore
            <cit>
              <ref xml:id="l58-Rd1e221">
                <name>Dionysius</name> V <title>De divinis nominibus</title>
              </ref>
              <bibl>XXX</bibl>
            </cit> 
            calls eternity 
            <quote xml:id="l58-Qd1ex21y">the age of time and the age of ages</quote>. 
            And
            <cit>
              <ref xml:id="l58-Rd1e236"><name>Anselmus</name> in <title>Proslogion</title></ref>
              <bibl>XXX</bibl>
            </cit>
            calls eternity 
            the age of ages, 
            from which he indicates that times and all other measures
            are effects of this measure then existing. <!-- transation help needed--> 
            And
            <ref xml:id="l58-Rav3kka" corresp="#l58-Qvm3dad">
              <name>Augustine</name> X <title>Confessionum</title>
            </ref> 
            <cit>
              <quote xml:id="l58-Qvm3dad"><!-- translation help needed -->
                while standing still eternity, 
                neither future nor past, 
                utters all things, 
                namely past times
              </quote>
            </cit>.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="l58-Dd1e264">
          <head xml:id="l58-Hcorria">Corollaries</head>
          <div xml:id="l58-Dd1e269">
            <head xml:id="l58-Hpcmpcm">Corollary 1</head>
            <p xml:id="l58-pcsocp">
              First corollary: 
              if an instant of time 
              were made fixed and immobile 
              and necessarily so per the impossible, 
              nevertheless it would not be eternity.
              This is clear because 
              none of the aforesaid conditions 
              would belong to it.
            </p> 
          </div>
          <div xml:id="l58-Dd1e278">
            <head xml:id="l58-Hscmscm">Corollary 2</head>
            <p xml:id="l58-sciqit">
              The second corollary: 
              an instant of eternity in infinity 
              is more simple and more actual than an instant of time. 
              From this it is able to be inferred 
              that in infinity 
              an instant of eternity is more indivisible 
              than an instant of time.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="l58-Dd1e287">
            <head xml:id="l58-Htcmtcm">Corollary 3</head>
            <p xml:id="l58-tcreii">
              The third corollary: 
              it is repugnant for contradictories to be true in eternity.
              This is clear because it is repugnant 
              that contradictories are true in an instant of time. 
              But an instant of eternity is more simple than an instant of time, 
              therefore it is even more unfitting 
              for contradictories to be true in an instant of eternity 
              than in an instant of time.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="l58-eqpamt">
              From which it is clear 
              that our assertions, affirmations, and negations 
              are in reference to a temporal measure.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="l58-Dd1e302">
            <head xml:id="l58-Hqcmqcm">Corollary 4</head>
            <p xml:id="l58-qcnsac">
              Fourth corollary:
              something new for eternity 
              coexisting with an instant of time
              does not argue for a succession or changeability of eternity, 
              but only argues for a succession of time. 
              as if something fixed point in a line were given, 
              the motion of the line around this point 
              would not, on account of this, change the point,
              and thus in the case of the corollary.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="l58-Dd1e316">
            <head xml:id="l58-Hqcrqcr">Corollary 5</head>
            <p xml:id="l58-qclepi">
              Fifth corollary:
              though eternity or 
              an instant of eternity is 
              in some way before time or after time 
              or simultaneous with time, 
              nevertheless it is not necessary that 
              it coexists with any instant of time whatsoever. 
              For to coexist requires the presence of eternity 
              but also the coexistence of an instance of time.
              Whence the savior says 
              in order to denote the priority of eternity with respect to time,
              <quote xml:id="l58-Qx1f3a5">
                before <name>Abraham</name> I am
              </quote>.
              And through this the eternity of God is indicated 
              because the word <mentioned>est</mentioned> 
              most especially belongs to God 
              and is said eternally about God.
              But, on account of our weakness, 
              it is permitted to say about God that he will be or that he was, 
              nevertheless, properly speaking, 
              only the word <mentioned>is</mentioned> is appropriate for God, 
              just as it is said in 
              <ref xml:id="l58-Rd1e343"><title>Exodus</title></ref> 
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="l58-Qd1e350">who is, sent me</quote>
              </cit> 
              etc., 
              and
              <cit>
                <quote xml:id="l58-Qd1e356" source="http://scta.info/resource/ex3_14">
                  I am who I am</quote>
              </cit>,
              and this is the name of eternity 
              and especially for that which does not change.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="l58-scanfp">
              But against this it is argued because, 
              if God were to have this priority with respect to time, 
              with a part before and a part after,
              then by the strength of this priority 
              he would be able to make it such that 
              the world never would have been created. 
              For if eternity precedes the world, 
              and is also now, 
              then it would follow also 
              that his causality and freedom precede the world, 
              and thus it would be possible for the world 
              never to have been produced.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="l58-pderei">
              <cit>
                <ref><name>Peter Damien</name></ref>
                <bibl>
                  <!--  Pier Damiani, De divina omnipotentia e altri opuscoli, ed. by Paolo Brezzi, trans. by Bruno ardi (Florence: Vallecchi, 1943),
                  pp. 66–68; nglish translation from: Peter amian, Selections from his ‘Letter on Divine Omnipotence’, trans. by Paul V. Spade
                  (1995), <http://pvspade.com/ogic/docs/damian.pdf>, p. 4. 
                  -->
                </bibl>
              </cit> 
              from this root 
              concedes the conclusion in a book which he wrote
              where he asks:
              whether God would be able to restore a virgin 
              such that she was never corrupted.
              Et this should not be understood 
              in such a way that he would be able 
              to give natural and equally perfect gifts, 
              now just as before,
              but merely whether he would be able to restore
              a virgin such that he was never corrupted. 
              And he concedes that God able to do so, 
              however because
              the
              <cit>
                <ref xml:id="l58-Rd1e382"><title>Article of Paris</title></ref>
                <bibl>XXX</bibl>
              </cit>
              maintains the opposite, 
              it is said that he is not able to do so.
              For even though God is in the same mode 
              now as he was before,
              because the matter is transitory
              and therefore 
              the matter which is present
              quickly flows into the past, 
              this implies the necessity of the corruption, 
              and thus it is not because of a defect 
              on the part of the divine power 
              but from the opposition 
              and incompatibility of things.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="l58-Dd1e392">
            <head xml:id="l58-Hsxmsxm">Corollary 6</head>
            <p xml:id="l58-apeeaa">
              Another proposition:
              the divine essence and any and all of the persons at the same time, 
              just as the are a single grade of perfection, 
              so they are the same eternity.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="l58-eqspei">
              From which it follows against
              Ex quo sequitur contra 
              <name>Master John of Rippa</name>
              that the supposite also in its personal existence 
              is measured by eternity and is eternity.
              For though there is there a distinction of supposites, 
              nevertheless there is an identity of perfection 
              because any and all of the persons at the same timem 
              are the same perfection.
              And this the person in its personal existence is formally eternity,
              and all three are measured by eternity.
              Nevertheless it is imagined by 
              <cit>
                <ref xml:id="l58-Rd1e407"><name>Rippa</name></ref>
                <bibl>XXX</bibl>
              </cit> 
              that eternity is formally a measure of an immeasurable thing,
              and consequently that the supposite, as such, 
              does not indicate a perfection absolutely,
              therefore it is not immediately measured by eternity, 
              but mediately 
              because it is the same in identity with the essence.
              Nevertheless <ref>I held elsewhere</ref>
              that the person does indicate a perfection absolutely,
              and all persons are the same perfection, 
              and this is sufficiently proved there.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="l58-seqema">
              It also follows that 
              the production of the Word and the spiration of the Holy Spirit 
              are measured by eternity. 
              From this it is clear the reason why the word of God, 
              though it has been produced, 
              nevertheless is always being produced. 
              The reason is the divine perfection and measure of eternity.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="l58-ehscad">
              And from this it follows 
              that it does not arise from the imperfection of that which produces the Word 
              because we say that the Word is always being produced. 
              For though in the production of the creature 
              this would from an imperfection of the cause 
              which would not suffice to give existence to a creature 
              perfectly and completely, 
              nevertheless existence has been given to it 
              by reason of the perfection in God and it is always given. 
              And from this follows a certain difference between the creature and God.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="l58-atuele">
              Nevertheless it should further 
              be known that, 
              though we speak thus by calling eternity a measure, 
              nevertheless eternity 
              itself <!-- a parte rei --> is nothing other than the immeasurable God, 
              and, just as it will be seen later,
              these predicates are imposed on account of our mode of conceiving, 
              because we conceive him as existing 
              we call him eternal, 
              and there is no diversity there
              except with respect to our mode of conceiving. 
              Therefore eternity indicates nothing 
              except that God is the most purest act 
              encompassing all perfection and infinity,
              and necessarily excluding all potentiality for acquiring or losing something, 
              such that we consider him an act for which it is repugnant <!-- contradictory --> to acquire or lose, 
              namely for acquiring or losing some kind of perfection,
              and just as he is the fullness of all perfection, 
              so he is called eternal, 
              and according to this mode he is eternity, 
              and similarly it should be about where he is and his ability to be in place.
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="l58-Dd1e434">
          <head xml:id="l58-Hprones">Propositions</head>
          <p xml:id="l58-pcddim">
            For an explanation of this some propositions are proposed 
            because Boethius, when explaining this matter, discusses through individual predicates.
          </p>
          <div xml:id="l58-Dd1e445">
            <head xml:id="l58-Hpritio">Proposition 1</head>
            <p xml:id="l58-sehilo">
              The first proposition is 
              that by however much the spiritual creature is more perfect 
              by the same degree they are able to occupy a greater amount of place. 
              because, regarding the corporeal, 
              it is not necessary that it occupy place unless according to its quantity,
              and according to what is fitting to the beauty of the universe.
              one thing is greater than another, 
              as the earth is greater than a human being
              and nevertheless a human being is more perfect, 
              therefore I speak about spiritual, 
              for just as the spiritual creature more greatly imitates God 
              in its essential perfection, so also in its occupation of space.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="l58-eqsoil">
              From which it follows 
              that if the highest creatable intelligence were supposed,
              then this would occupy the finite space beyond the heavens.
              For if the occupation of place is part of its essential perfection,
              then, when this is infinite, 
              it would occupy infinite place.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="l58-squppo">
              But it might be asked 
              whether the spiritual creature 
              under however much place would be able to be situated.
              For which it should be imagined 
              that any creature determines for itself its quantity of place which it occupies
              according to the quantity of its own essential perfection,
              nevertheless it is possible from the absolute power of God to be situated in a greater or lesser amount of space 
              because it seems unlikely that  
              the human soul would be able to be situated in some small part of the body, 
              such that if a human being were produced successively, 
              then the soul would first inform a small part, 
              and in this way, it seems unlikely that  
              that it would be ale to occupy an infinitely small part.
              <!-- translation difficult here. -->
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="l58-Dd1e460">
              <head xml:id="l58-Hspospo">Proposition 2</head>
            <p xml:id="l58-apdesr">
              Another proposition: 
              God is not properly in place, 
              at least not when speaking about existence in place circumscriptively 
              since there is no doubt about this, 
              but rather place is in god, 
              and this is greatest difficulty regarding the present subject matter.
              And regrading this there are several authoritative sayings of Augustine
              which are cited by the
              <cit>
                <ref xml:id="l58-Rd1e472">the <name>Master</name> in the third distinction of the first book</ref>
                <bibl>XXX</bibl>
              </cit>. 
              Whence
              <ref xml:id="l58-Rd1e483"><name>Augustine</name></ref>
              says: 
              that
              <quote xml:id="l58-Qg8cccq">
                God is not properly anywhere, 
                but things are in him
              </quote>
            </p>
            <p xml:id="l58-sqessr">
              It follows that, 
              from the fact that God is diverse places either successively or at the same time, 
              this is not an argument for some kind of change in God or some kind of potentiality, 
              but only a change in things.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="l58-Dd1e496">
            <head xml:id="l58-Htpotpo">Proposition 3</head>
            <p xml:id="l58-aplrcs">
              Another proposition: 
              imaginary place or location 
              
              as divisible 
              
              and the capacity of the creature infinitely recedes from the divine capacity 
              
              and this is rather difficult to imagine 
              
              but nevertheless there is a point to the difficulty
              
              whence it should be imagined thus that God by reason of his immensity is an intelligible sphere whose center is everywhere 
              and whose circumference is nowhere, 
              then from the immensity of God 
              God concurs aptitudinally for receiving a creature situationally.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="l58-peispi">
              Primo ergo imaginandum est 
              divinam immensitatem, 
              deinde imaginandum est spatium infinitum 
              coexistens sibi causatum ab eo ex quo consurgit tanquam effectus 
              potentialitas recipiendi creaturas, 
              ita quod imaginandum est quod illud 
              spatium imaginarium est infinitum minus perfectum ad Recipiendum 
              creaturas quam ipse deus. ita quod deus Recipit creaturas et 
              etiam spatium imaginarium, 
              tamen deus in infinitum perfectius 
              Recipit creaturas in suo modo recipiendi et deinde spatium 
              habet possibilitatem recipiendi creaturas emanentes a deo. et quod deus 
              est capax creaturarum in nobilissimo genere. 
              Et a deo emanat spatium, 
              sicut ab aeternitatem emanatur tempus 
              et omnis alia successiva duratio, 
              et sic patet imaginatio.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="l58-Dd1e519">
            <head xml:id="l58-Hqpoqpo">Quarta propositio</head>
            <p xml:id="l58-apicvn">
              Alia propositio: 
              immensus locus intelligibilis 
              potest solum divinam essentiam locare imaginadum est proportionaliter, 
              licet idem sit a parte rei adaequate aeternitas et deus, 
              ita locabilitas est ipsemet, 
              tamen consideremus eum secundum aliqui rationem 
              secundum quam est locus immensus et sicut aeternitas est mensura 
              dei Ita ille locus est locus adaequatus dei, 
              et etiam immensus locus intelligibilis, 
              sicut aeterna duratio solum mensurat divinam perfectionem, 
              nihilominus divina locabilitas est formaliter. 
              Unde deus habet multas proprietates quas non possumus exprimere. 
              Ideo 
              <cit>
                <ref xml:id="l58-Rd1e528"><name>philosophus</name></ref>
                <bibl>XXX</bibl>
              </cit> 
              sufficienter posuit 
              quod deus est sphera intelligibilis cuius centrum 
              est ubi circumferentia vero nusquam.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="l58-Dd1e538">
            <head xml:id="l58-Hqaoqao">Quinta propositio</head>
            <p xml:id="l58-apqadl">
              Alia propositio: quanto Res est 
              perfectior tanto magis intimatur deo et appropinquat ad 
              divinam 
              <app>
                <lem n="divinam"/>
                <rdg wit="#SV">
                  <del rend="strikethrough">essentiam</del>
                </rdg>
              </app> 
              localitatem.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="l58-Dd1e558">
            <head xml:id="l58-Hsxosxo">Sexta propositio</head>
            <p xml:id="l58-aplidi">
              Alia propositio: 
              licet creaturae variae valde 
              intimentur a deo et diversimode vocentur in eo participando 
              intimationem variae, 
              nihilominus tamen deus immense intimatur creaturae 
              quantum est ex parte sui, 
              nam sicut deus unico gradu agendi 
              nihil actionis agit diversos effectus, 
              ita unico gradu 
              concurrit intimando creaturas sibi, 
              et sic creaturae intimantur deo 
              infinite.
            </p>
          </div>
          <div xml:id="l58-Dd1e567">
            <head xml:id="l58-Hsmpsmp">Septima propositio</head>
            <p xml:id="l58-apdmid">
              Alia propositio de intimatione ex gratificatione. Unde dicitur quod 
              deus in gratificatione quantum est ex parte sui non magis intimatur 
              creaturae, sed per hoc creatura magis intimatur deo.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="l58-idnmid">
              ideo deus non venit 
              ad creaturam, licet deus multipliciter pulset creaturam, 
              sed magis creatura ad deum. tamen quia ex propriis viribus creatura 
              non venit ad deum, nec intimatur gratificatione 
              in deo. Ideo ista intimatio attribuitur deo et non creaturae 
              et per hoc proprium argumentum creaturae fortiter et magis intimatur 
              deo.
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="l58-Dd1e581">
          <head xml:id="l58-Hconsio">Conclusio</head>
          <p xml:id="l58-edpfpe">
            Ex dictis patet de proprietatibus dei quantum ad ea quae concernunt duo 
            praedicata, scilicet, praedicamentum <mentioned>ubi</mentioned>, 
            et quando dicit tamen 
            <cit>
              <ref xml:id="l58-Rd1e593"><name>Boetius</name></ref>
              <bibl>XXX</bibl>
            </cit> 
            quod deus non est proprie in praedicamento, 
            nec est proprie substantia sed <unclear>supscribam</unclear>, 
            <cb ed="#SV" n="b"/><!--SV270vb-->
            tamen aliquo modo reducitur in genere substantiae et relationis, 
            et non in aliquo aliorum 
            quia alia derivantur ab illo, et est causa 
            illorum, scilicet, tam loci quam temporis, 
            et sic patet de eius simplicitate, 
            tamen de eius simplicitate magis inquireretur, 
            quando fiet mentio, 
            utrum in deo sint aliquae formalitates ponendae, 
            et cetera.
          </p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>